Leason Heberling Adams Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Leason Heberling Adams Papers 1919-1968
MSS78279
Adams, Leason Heberling, 1887-1969
500 items 4 containers 2 linear feet
Manuscript Division Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Geophysicist, consultant, and educator. Correspondence, writings, notes and notebooks, and printed matter relating to Adams's research and publication in geophysics and earth sciences.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the Library's online catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically therein.
People
Adams, Leason Heberling, 1887-1969.; Cohen, Lewis H.--Correspondence.; Day, Arthur L. (Arthur Louis), 1869-1960--Correspondence.; Sosman, Robert B. (Robert Browning), 1881-1967--Correspondence.
Organizations
Geological Society of America--Correspondence.; National Academy of Sciences (U.S.)--Correspondence.
Subjects
Earth sciences.; Geophysics.; Nephelite.; Thermodynamics.; Wollastonite.
Occupations
Consultants.; Educators.; Geophysicists.
Administrative Information
Provenance
The papers of Leason Heberling Adams, geophysical, science consultant, educator, and author, were given to the Library of Congress by his widow, Freda R. Adams, in 1972.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Leason Heberling Adams are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1887, 16 Jan. Born, Cherryvale, Kans.
1906 B.S., chemical engineering, University of Illinois, Champaign-Urbana, Ill.
1908 Married Jeannette Blaisdell
1910-1936 Physical chemist, Geophysical Laboratory, Carnegie Institution, Washington, D.C.
1924 Awarded Edward Longstreth Medal from the Franklin Institute, Philadelphia, Pa.
1936-1952 Director, Geophysical Laboratory, Carnegie Institution, Washington, D.C.
1941 Sc.D., Tufts University, Medford, Mass.
1948 Awarded Presidential Medal for Merit
1950 Awarded William Bowie Medal by the American Geophysical Union
1956 Married Freda R. Ostraw
1958-1963 Visiting professor, geophysics, University of California, Los Angeles, Calif.
1963 Professor-in-residence, University of California, Los Angeles, Calif.
1969, 20 Aug. Died, Silver Spring, Md.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Leason Heberling Adams (1887-1969) span the years 1919-1968. The collection consists of personal and professional correspondence, notebooks, notes, published writings on scientific research, and miscellaneous printed matter that are organized into the following series: Correspondence, Writings, and Miscellany.
The Correspondence concerns research and publication in the field of geophysics and earth science. Among the correspondents are Lewis Cohen, Arthur Day, Robert Sosman, the National Academy of Sciences, the Geological Society of America, and colleagues with whom Adams engaged in joint research and publication. The largest amount of correspondence is between Adams and Cohen pertaining to their research in relation to nepheline and wollastonite analyses and their joint authorship of a paper published by the American Journal of Science in 1966.
Typescripts, galley proofs, and reprint copies of published articles by Adams, as well as articles coauthored with other scientists, make up the bulk of the Writings. These writings date from 1919 to 1966 and cover results of research in pressure measurements and control.
The Miscellany consists of directories, programs, and printed matter, but the most significant items in this file are the notes and notebooks, 1921-1922, related to Adams's research in thermodynamics and chemical thermodynamics. Also included in this series are the notes and drafts of Adams's published writings.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged in three series:
Correspondence, 1933-1968
Writings, 1919-1966
Miscellany, 1919-1966
http://lccn.loc.gov/mm81078279
Container List
- Correspondence, 1933-1968 (Box 1)
  Letters and memoranda from colleagues, scientific organizations, and institutions.
  Arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent and therein chronologically.
  - Bassett, William A., 1965 (Box 1)
  - Cohen, Lewis H., 1965-1966, (2 folders) (Box 1)
  - Day, Arthur L. and Ruth E., 1933, 1964 (Box 1)
  - Geological Society of America, 1958-1961 (Box 1)
  - Goranson, R. W., 1953-1958 (Box 1)
  - McGraw-Hill Book Co., 1965 (Box 1)
  - National Academy of Sciences, 1958-1964 (Box 1)
  - National Science Foundation, 1965 (Box 1)
  - Sosman, Robert B., 1960-1964 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous, 1936-1968, undated (Box 1)
- Writings, 1919-1966 (Box 1-2)
  Typescripts, reports, and reprint copies of published writings coauthored with other scientists.
  Arranged chronologically by year of publication.
  - Articles (Box 1)
    - "Thermostats for Very High Temperatures," Journal of the Optical Society of America and Review of Scientific Instruments, Nov. 1924 (Box 1)
    - "The Annealing of Glass as a Physical Problem," Journal of The Franklin Institute, July 1933 (Box 1)
    - "Simplified Apparatus for High Hydrostatic Pressures," The Review of Scientific Instruments, Apr. 1936 (Box 1)
    - "The Earth's Interior, Its Nature and Composition," The Scientific Monthly, Mar. 1937 (Box 1)
  - Reports, "Preliminary Survey on Establishment of a High Pressure Scale," 1965 (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous untitled (Box 2)
  - Writings published with others (Box 2)
    - Davis, Briant L., 1962-1966 (Box 2)
    - Goranson, R. W., 1933 (Box 2)
    - Waxler, Roy M., 1960-1964 (Box 2)
    - White, Walter P., 1919 (Box 2)
    - Williamson, Erskine D., 1919 (Box 2)
- Miscellany, 1919-1966 (Box 2-4)
  Notes and notebooks relating to Adams's early research and printed matter and writings by others.
  Arranged alphabetically by type of material.
  - Notes (Box 2)
    - Thermodynamics, 1919-1920 (Box 2)
    - Chemical thermodynamics, 1921-1922 (Box 2)
    - "Enthalphy Changes from Melting Curves in Binary Silicate Systems," 1965 (Box 3)
    - "Elliptically Prolonged Light" (Box 3)
    - Thermodynamics (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous (3 folders) (Box 3)
  - Printed matter, (1 folder) (Box 3, Box 4)
  - Proposals (Box 4)
  - Writings of others, 1951-1966 (Box 4)